Hi, everybody. My name
is Dr. Joseph Holloway,
and in this session,
we're going to be covering
rheumatic fever, vasculitis,
and cardiomyopathy,
which are three different
conditions that are
brought about by separate
and unique microbes.
Now, the specific
diseases that we're going
to be discussing today
are rheumatic fever,
Rocky Mountain Spotted
Fever, and Chagas disease.
So you're going to want
to be able to understand
the basic epidemiology
associated with
each one of those,
along with the etiology.
So being able to identify
and describe the microbial
pathogen that causes each
one of those conditions.
You're going to want to
be able to understand the
clinical presentation of each
one and the pathogenesis,
so what's basically
happening during the course
of the infection, along
with being able to explain
the basic diagnosis and
treatment for each disease.
Okay so our first condition is
going to be rheumatic fever.
Now rheumatic fever is
considered a multi-system
disease which means it's
going to affect different
areas of your body and
that's going to happen
because of an autoimmune
-like reaction. So this is
technically a type 2
hypersensitivity reaction where
your immune system is
going to raise antibodies
against antigens on the
offending microbe, which
in this case is Streptococcus
pyogenes. And then
those antibodies have the
ability to then cross-react
with different cells and
tissues in your body.
Now, the effects of rheumatic
fever are not typically
seen during the primary
infection with strep,
but instead are going to
be seen a couple of weeks
later after that. And
this is generally going to
be associated with cases
of strep throat, so
pharyngitis, untreated upper
respiratory infections.
Now, there's going to
be a little bit of lag
time between the initial
infection and then
any sort of rheumatic
fever symptoms because of
the time that it takes
to create antibodies.
All right, now the main
group of individuals that
are going to be affected
by this typically are going
to be children with an
average age of about 10.
And this is certainly
going to be associated
with impoverished
areas of the world,
so different types of
countries that have or
that don't have a
robust medical system.
If you consider the
incidence in affluent
countries, it's going
to be relatively low due
to the fact that cases
of strep throat can be
identified and treated
relatively easily. So
let's talk a little
bit about strep.
All right, so streptococcus
pyogenes that causes
rheumatic fever falls into
the group A streptococcus
landsfield grouping, which
is based on a surface
-level carbohydrate known
as the C-carbohydrate.
Now, some other aspects of
strep that you would expect
are based on, you know,
just the name of the genus.
So streptococcus, you
would expect to see coccus
-shaped circular cells that
are arranged in chains. And
so that's where streptococcus
comes from, in addition
to being gram-positive
right after a gram stain.
And you can see
that represented in
the microscopic
image on the slide.
Now, some of the
other points made here
are really ways that
you can differentiate
strep from other
different varieties of
microbes, different
types of strep or staph.
And so the first note to
make, diagnostically speaking,
is that strep is going
to be catalase negative.
Now, catalase negative is
going to be a feature of
the streptococcus group in
addition to the enterococcus
group, which is
relatively related to the
streptococcus group, but
that's going to be different
than staph, which is going
to be catalase positive.
Now, within the strep and
enterococcus group, you have
to have a way of diagnostically
separating those.
And one way that you can
do that is using hemolysis.
Now, strep pyogenes group A
tends to be beta hemolytic,
and that's brought about
by a virulence factor,
which is an exotoxin that
is secreted by the bacterial
cells known as streptolysin
S and streptolysin O.
So what happens is that
those toxins are capable
of degrading red blood
cells. And so if you grow
these bacteria on a blood
agar plate in a laboratory
the red blood cells will
be completely broken
down by the exotoxin and
the red color of the plate
will basically revert
back to a clear agar plate
now streptolysin s is
really the reason why
that happens because
that's an oxygen stable
exotoxin whereas streptolysin
o is not oxygen stable
streptolysin o is
important though because
Streptolysin O is immunogenic,
and the immune system
will raise antibodies
against that. So that's a
good diagnostic tool to be
able to identify whether
an individual had group
A strep infection or not.
Streptolysin S is
not immunogenic.
Now, within the beta-hemolytic
group, you have to have
a way of differentiating
those, right? Because group
A, B, and C are all beta
hemolytic, so you have to have
a way of differentiating
those. And that's where other
different tests like the
susceptibility to bacitracin
come in. So group A strep
tends to be susceptible to
bacitracin, whereas B and
C would be resistant to it.
You could also run
something like a
PYR test where group
A strep would be
positive and B and
C would be negative.
now the last point to make
here is about yet another
virulence factor which is
known as the m protein and
the m protein is really
important in rheumatic fever
because it is the antibodies
that are raised against
the m protein that are
going to be the cross
-reactive antibodies that
cause the issues in rheumatic
fever now from the perspective
of the bacterial cell
the m protein as a virulence
factor, is really just
a mechanism by which it is
going to try to evade the
immune system. So the M
protein is anti-phagocytic.
Now, in addition to that,
strep pyogenes will
secrete a capsule, and that
capsule happens to be
created from hyaluronic
acid. Now, because hyaluronic
acid is also naturally
found in human connective
tissues, the bacterium
basically has a capsule
that is inert in terms
of being identified by
the host immune system.
Now it's that host
immune system that's
actually responsible
for rheumatic fever.
So in the figure you could
see the basic process of
group A strep infection
associated with the epithelium
in the throat and then the
activation of the immune
system due to that infection
which is to be expected.
As a result, in rheumatic
fever, the immune system
then is going to target
normal host proteins
like cardiac myosin in the
heart and laminin in the
heart valves, and this
is going to be due to
molecular mimicry. So
antibodies and T-cells that were
initially formed against
the streptococcal M
protein mistakenly cross
-react with the normal host
proteins that happen to
be structurally similar,
and then that triggers
inflammation and damage.
Now, there's no specific lab
test for rheumatic fever,
but there is instead the
Jones criteria as a system
for diagnosing acute rheumatic
fever. So first, what
you need is evidence of a
preceding group A strep infection.
And that could be done
with serological testing.
So looking at antibody
titers for streptolysin O,
or maybe DNase B, which
is another secreted enzyme
produced by strep that can
be used diagnostically.
Or even more simply,
just a positive
throat culture or
a rapid strep test.
So once the previous
infection is established,
you could then use the
Jones criteria, which
is a set of major criteria
to identify rheumatic
fever, along with some
minor criteria that
you can see here. So
things like fever or a
previous bout of rheumatic
fever, among others.
As for the major criteria,
the term Jones is an
acronym, most of which is
outlined here on the slide.
so first j stands for
joints and that is going to
be associated with the
polyarthritis that you see
in rheumatic fever early
on so polyarthritis means
that it's going to be
affecting multiple different
joints and it's also
migratory so the location of
the joints is going to
change over time it's also
generally associated with
the larger joints in the
body and it's going to
affect them asymmetrically.
So just because you have
a pain in a joint on the
right hand side doesn't
mean that you necessarily
have a pain in the
associated joint on the left.
All right, I'm going
to skip over O for the
moment here, and
that brings us to N,
which is nodules. So
these are subcutaneous,
small, painless nodules,
like you can see in the image
on the slide, that typically
are going to be seen on
the elbows, sometimes also
on the hands or the feet.
All right, E
stands for erythema
marginatum, which is a
non-itchy rash, which
you could also see
here on the slide.
And this is generally
going to be seen
as these pink ring
-shaped lesions with
pale centers and
slightly raised borders.
Usually they're going to be
seen on the trunk
and the limbs.
And lastly is
Seidenham's chorea, which
is actually a
neurological disorder.
That's going to be
characterized by uncontrollable
spasmodic movements, typically
of the head and the face,
sometimes the tongue as
well, and the limbs also.
Interestingly,
this tends to manifest in
females more than
it does males.
Okay, so the letter
I left out was O,
which you could think
more about like the
shape of a heart and which
is also the most life
-threatening component
of rheumatic fever.
Now, the condition can
lead to pancarditis, which
takes into account all the
layers of the heart and it
can lead to endocarditis
myocarditis or pericarditis
so like endocarditis
rheumatic fever will
often have an
associated heart murmur
due to vegetations on
the heart valves and
this will often affect
the left side of the
heart most commonly the
mitral valve pericarditis
can be associated
with pain in the chest
And myocardial
inflammation can affect the
electrical conduction,
leading to a disrupted ECG.
From a histological standpoint,
the inflamed myocardium
will also display
structures known as
Ashoff bodies, which
are granulomas in
the connective tissue
of the heart due to
chronic inflammation.
Now, those contain
Anishkau cells, which
are abnormal
macrophages, and you can
see both of those
images on the slide.
Now, it's structures like
these that can lead to
scarring, and if there's a
repeated exposure to group A
strep infections, rheumatic
fever can ultimately become
chronic, leading to more
scarring and the potential
for valve stenosis or even
congestive heart failure.
Now, in terms of treating
acute rheumatic fever,
even though it's an immune
-mediated condition, you
would want to use antibiotics
to be sure that there's
no bacteria that remain
that could cause an
infection, in addition to
using anti-inflammatories.
okay so we're going to
move on to bacterial
vasculitis specifically
Rocky Mountain spotted
fever the condition is
caused by a species of
bacteria known as
Rickettsia Rickettsii Now,
rickettsial bacteria are
kind of unique because
they are obligate
intracellular pathogens.
They can't exist on their
own outside of other cells.
And the reason for that
is because they lack
some of the genes to
make their own energy.
So really, they're
just basically
energy parasites
of other cells.
Now, in terms of the
bacterial profile,
rickettsial bacteria
technically have a gram-negative
type wall, but they are very
difficult to gram stain.
And so in order
to visualize them,
typically other staining
procedures are going
to be utilized,
like Gimsa staining.
All right, now, in order
to contract rickettsia, you
need that bacterium to be
vectored. And so when thinking
about Rocky Mountain spotted
fever, it's really just
as important to talk about
the vector as much as it
is to talk about the causative
agent, the bacterium.
So the vector for the
disease is going to be the
dog tick, which is known
as Dermocenter variabilis.
And the distribution
of the tick is
basically going to
be everywhere in the
United States east of
the Rocky Mountains.
So the naming convention of
the disease is a little bit
of a misnomer. So it really
is not associated with
the West or with the Rocky
Mountains. It's going to be
much more endemic, seen
much more frequently in the
eastern United States, specifically
the southeastern United
States. And you can even
see on the map on the slide,
basically there's a belt
between North Carolina and
Oklahoma where most of the
cases are going to be seen.
Now, that's not to
say that you can't
see it sporadically
in the west also.
In that case, it's
not going to be the
dog tick that's going
to be the vector.
There's another
species of dermacenter
known as dermacenter
andersoni that
will be the vector
in that location.
The reservoir for the bacteria
is primarily the infected
ticks. So they harbor the
bacteria and they transmit
the bacteria. So humans
and other animals are kind
of basically accidental
hosts because they're really
not required for the
completion of the life cycle.
But the animals can
act as reservoirs,
right? So rodents or
rabbits can act as
reservoirs or maybe
as amplifying hosts.
But the ticks really are
the permanent natural
reservoir. are. So they
carry the bacteria, and they
actually pass them to their
offspring through a process
known as transovarial
transmission. So basically, a
female tick that's infected
with rickettsial bacteria
can transmit the bacteria
directly to her eggs, and
so the larvae, as they
hatch, are going to be born
with the bacteria. So you
don't really necessarily
need a secondary host like
a human or another animal.
All right, now if a human
does contract the bacteria
following a tick bite,
the bacteria is going to
enter into the body and then
spread in the bloodstream.
So there's bacteremia
associated with this, and
usually that's going to be
in the window of about 7
to 10 days before the
symptoms are going to start.
At that point, the bacteria
that are going to attach
and invade the vascular
endothelial cells, right,
the lining of the blood
vessels throughout the body.
And it's really that
widespread invasion
that's going to lead
to the vasculitis.
So what do we expect
to see in a patient
that has Rocky
Mountain Spotted Fever?
So early on in the infection,
it's going to appear like
a patient just has some sort
of viral infection maybe
a flu it's going to just show
you know basic nonspecific
symptoms something like
a fever you know general
pain vomiting or a headache
now the headache could be
a good indicator so typically
the headache is going
to be severe and that's going
to be due to the vasculitis
of the vessels in the brain
leading to that prominent
headache so it's certainly
something to consider.
Now within a couple of
days you would see then
the characteristic rash
associated with the
condition which is going
to stem from the vasculitis
and the hemorrhaging
of the of the vessels.
Now that rash is typically
going to start on
the wrists and the ankles
and then move up the
extremities to the to
the trunk of the body.
Now due to the vasculitis
and the inflammation
you know, the leakage of
the blood vessels, the
hemorrhaging, the clotting,
and the effect on the
blood flow then has the
ability to affect critical
organs in the body.
So there can be damage
to the brain, the lungs,
or the heart. So Rocky
Mountain spotted fever
can rapidly lead to fatal
complications if left
undiagnosed or unchecked.
In terms of diagnosis,
it's usually going
to be based on clinical
symptoms as well as
a history of potential
tick exposure rather
than waiting on
laboratory test results.
Now some tests that you
can conduct would be
serological testing to
identify antibodies in the
patient or trying to identify
the rickettsial bacteria
either by way of a skin
biopsy or a PCR method.
Because the infection progresses
rapidly and can become
fatal, typically treatment
with an antibiotic like
doxycycline is usually
going to be started almost
immediately if Rocky Mountain
spotted fever is suspected.
All right, so the last
condition we're going
to discuss here is going
to be Chagas disease.
otherwise known as
American trypanosomiasis.
And I want to emphasize
American just to
differentiate this from
the African trypanosomes.
All right, so Chagas
disease is caused by a
protozoal parasite known
as trypanosoma cruzi.
And trypanosomes, along with
other related organisms,
have the ability to change
morphological form throughout
their life cycle. Now,
in terms of trypanosoma
cruzi, there are two
morphological forms associated
with it, the trypamastigote
and the amastigote form. So
the trypamastigote form is
going to be the infective
form that you're going to
find in the human blood very
early on in the infection,
and that's highlighted
in the first image on the
slide with the black arrow.
Now there are some structural
features to the
trypamastigote form.
First is the undulating
membrane. So a trypimastogote
form of trypanosoma cruzi
will typically take on
this kind of C-shaped
format, and the undulating
membrane can be seen on
the top of the parasite. So
this is a flagellum that
runs along the length of one
side of the parasite and
is housed within the plasma
membrane, making this kind
of sail-like structure,
And that's going to
terminate in a flagellum,
which you can see down at
the bottom of the parasite.
Now, the trypamastigote
form has the ability to then
identify, target, and
invade different cells and
tissues within the body, at
which point it's going to
change morphological form
into what's known as the
amastigote form. And the
amastigote form is going to be
a form that is capable of
dividing very frequently.
So this is an intracellular
form, and it doesn't
have any of the same
structural features as
the tripomastigote form
would have. So there
is no flagellum. There's
no undulating membrane.
It's a much smaller
cell, much more reduced.
And as it is housed within
the cell, it's going
to undergo division,
creating a group of cells
within that invaded cell.
And it's going to create
basically this structure
that looks like a nest
or a clump of amastogote
cells known as a pseudocyst.
It's not really a
true cyst because the
parasite is not actually
secreting any sort of cyst
wall. It's just housed
within the infected cell.
all right so we're talking
about another condition here
that requires a vector
and in the case of chagas
disease the vector is known
as the reduvid bug otherwise
known as the kissing or the
assassin bug now cases of
chagas disease then are
going to be correlated to the
distribution of the vector
So typically, you're going
to see cases in Central
and South America, although
raduvid bugs have been
identified as far north as Texas.
Now, the bug tends
to bite at nighttime,
and it will also
tend to bite around
the head or the face
of an individual.
That's also why it got
its name, the kissing bug.
Now, at the time that
it's taking a blood meal,
it will also defecate,
and in the feces, you will
have the parasite in
trypomastigote form. So now
the parasite has an entry
point into the body.
Now, once the
parasite gets into
the bloodstream
and the lymphatics,
it could basically go anywhere.
And so even though it
can basically invade any
nucleated cell, it tends
to have a stronger affinity
for specific tissues in
the body. So things like
muscle tissue, the liver,
the spleen, the central
or peripheral nervous
system, among others. And
once it invades a tissue,
it will again convert
to the amastigote form.
It will begin to undergo
division and create
pseudocysts within the tissue.
So wherever the bug bites
and the parasite enters
into the body there's
going to be a localized
reaction that's referred
to as a shagoma and
you can see that down on
the bottom of the slide
with the picture highlighted
by the black arrow
now i already said that
the bug likes to bite
around the head and
the face and oftentimes
the bite is going to be
close enough to the eye where
the parasite could either
be rubbed into the eye
or can just gain access
by way of the conjunctiva.
And if that's the case,
the swelling is going
to be around the eye,
and that's referred
to as Romagna's sign.
And you can see that
highlighted in the picture
with the red arrows.
Now, both of these are going
to be hallmark physical
indicators of the acute
phase of Chagas disease.
Over the next few weeks,
an individual can either
be asymptomatic or could
have just some general
mild symptoms, you
know, things like fever,
body aches, fatigue,
along with potential
swelling of the spleen or
the liver. And ultimately,
those symptoms can
resolve on their own.
Now, most people are going
to enter into a lifelong
asymptomatic stage where
the parasites are basically
hidden and don't really
cause any issues but some
other people are going to
progress to a symptomatic
stage anywhere from years
to decades later and can
display some pretty
significant complications
because of the chronic
infection like heart issues that
include inflammation
arrhythmias or just enlargement
of the heart now other
complications that could
be seen in the chronic form
of the disease are known
as megaesophagus and
megacolon. And that's going
to be due to the parasite
targeting the autonomic
nerves and the smooth
muscle of the GI tract over
time. And this causes the
characteristic enlargement,
the loss of the muscle
tone, and will disrupt
things like peristalsis
and has the potential
to even inhibit the
act of swallowing.
So diagnosing Chagas disease
really depends on the
stage of the infection. In
the acute stage, you could
look for parasites in a blood
smear or a tissue biopsy,
or you could use a technique
like PCR to detect it.
In chronic Chagas disease,
the parasite levels in
the blood drop pretty
significantly, and so that
makes things like microscopy
a little less effective.
So at that point, diagnosis
is really going to rely
on serological testing.
Now in the acute
phase, you can also
use antiparasitic
medications to clear
the organism from
the bloodstream.
But in the chronic form,
medications unfortunately
can't really reverse
any type of tissue or
organ damage that might
have already occurred. So
that concludes the
lecture. I just wanted
to thank everyone
for listening, and I
wanted to provide the
link for feedback.